Guide to the Lucile Lomen Collection
Stanford University. Libraries.
Department of Special Collections and University Archives
Lucile Lomen collection
1920-2004
SC0776
Lomen, Lucile.
2 Linear feet (4 boxes)
This collection includes correspondence by, to, and about Lucile Lomen; legal materials such as case notes, briefs, and legal decisions; newspaper, magazine, and journal clippings or excerpts; writings authored by Lomen; General Electric documents and publications, including some on their nuclear aircraft propulsion program; and autobiographical letters, essays and interview transcripts.
Department of Special Collections and University Archives Green Library 557 Escondido Mall Stanford, CA 94305-6064 Email: specialcollections@stanford.edu Phone: (650) 725-1022 URL: http://library.stanford.edu/spc
Administrative Information
Provenance
This collection was given to the Stanford University Archives by Ann Sandstrom and Jennie Berry Chandra in 2005.
Information about Access
This collection is open for research; materials must be requested at least 48 hours in advance of intended use.
Biographical/Historical Sketch
Lucile Lomen was born in Nome, Alaska on August 21, 1920, the second of five children of Alfred and Mildred (nee Lehmann) Lomen. At least partially inspired by her grandfather, Gudbran J. Lomen, as a young girl, she decided that she wanted to become a lawyer. Her family moved to Seattle in 1934, where she graduated from Queen Anne High School in 1937. She was awarded a one-year scholarship to Whitman College in Walla Walla, Washington, which she attended and from which she graduated with honors in 1941. Upon her graduation from the University of Washington Law School in 1944, she was elected to the Order of the Coif.
A few months before her graduation from law school, Lomen was selected by Supreme Court Justice William O. Douglas to serve as his law clerk for the October 1944 term. When she reported for duty in September 1944, she became the first woman to clerk for a Supreme Court Justice.
After one busy year in Washington, Lomen returned to Seattle, where she worked in the Washington state Attorney General's office. She remained at this job for three years, save for a trip to Europe with her maternal grandparents from the summer of 1946 to early 1947. In 1948, Lomen left the Attorney General's office to work for General Electric. Initially employed as a lawyer in Richland, Washington, Lomen served in many different capacities in several different states during her tenure with the company. She retired in 1983 and remained on the East Coast, where she was then living, for a few years before returning to Seattle, where she died on June 21, 1996.
Description of the Collection
This collection includes correspondence by, to, and about Lucile Lomen; legal materials such as case notes, briefs, and legal decisions; newspaper, magazine, and journal clippings or excerpts; writings authored by Lomen; General Electric documents and publications, including some on their nuclear aircraft propulsion program; and autobiographical letters, essays and interview transcripts. Correspondence addressed to Lomen is from Edith Allen, Walter Beals, Vera and Vern Countryman, William O. Douglas, Tom Edwards, Judson F. Falknor, John M. Ferren, Helen Gaylord, Donald G. Graham, Eugene Gressman, Julia Benton Hopkins and Helen Vincent Dolan, Mr. and Mrs. Thorulf Lehmann (Lomen's grandparents), Chester Maxey, William G. McLaren, Conrad Oberdorfer, Vilhjalmur Stefansson, Smith Troy, and Mabel Walker Willebrandt.
Other materials of note in this collection include a single-page essay entitled "October Term 1944," about her experience at the Supreme Court; her May 1991 Whitman oral history interview; and Lomen's outgoing correspondence during her trip to Europe, 1946-1947. Also included in the collection is the correspondence of Jennie Berry Chandra, 2004, who assembled some of the materials in this collection in the course of her research on Lomen.
Access Terms
Beals, Walter B.; Countryman, Vern.; Douglas, William O. (William Orville), 1898-; Ferren, John M.; General Electric Company.; Gressmen, Eugene.; Lomen, Lucile.; Maxey, Chester Collins, 1890-; Oberdorfer, Conrad W.; Stefansson, Vilhjalmur, 1879-1962.; United States. Supreme Court.; Law clerks--United States
Collection Contents
- Autobiographical/Biographical Materials (Box 1, Folder 1)
- Photo (Box 1, Folder 2)
- Report Cards (Box 1, Folder 3)
- Honors, Recommendations, Achievements (Box 1, Folder 4)
- Whitman Interview, 1991 May (Box 1, Folder 5)
- Whitman Interview, 1994 Jun (Box 1, Folder 6)
- Whitman Interview, 1994 Oct (Box 1, Folder 7)
- Materials Relating to Lomen's Death (Box 1, Folder 8)
- Correspondence Relating to Douglas' Selection of Lomen (Box 1, Folder 9)
- Certificate of Appointment as Clerk (Box 1, Folder 10)
- Notes and Memos from Lomen's Time in Supreme Court (Box 1, Folder 11)
- Cases in Which Lomen Was Involved, 1946-1949 (Box 1, Folder 12)
- Habeas Corpus Memos, 1946 Jul-1949 May (Box 1, Folder 13)
- Briefs -- Washington Cases 11827-29643 (Box 1, Folder 14)
- Briefs -- Washington Cases 29934-30281 (Box 1, Folder 15)
- Briefs -- Washington Cases 30461-30480 (Box 2, Folder 1)
- Briefs -- Washington Cases 30486-30601 (Box 2, Folder 2)
- Briefs -- Washington Cases in Which Lomen's Involvement Is Unclear (Box 2, Folder 3)
- Materials Related to Lomen's Hiring By GE, 1948 (Box 2, Folder 4)
- Career -- GE (Box 2, Folder 5)
- GE Evaluations, Paperwork, Other Papers about Lomen's Position/Work (Box 2, Folder 6)
- GE Nuclear Aircraft Propulsion Program (Box 2, Folder 7)
- GE WWII War Claims (Box 2, Folder 8)
- Career -- General Learning Corporation, Elfun (Box 2, Folder 9)
- Application to Massachusetts Bar (Box 2, Folder 10)
- Application to New York Bar (Box 2, Folder 11)
- Douglas Letters of Recommendation (Box 2, Folder 12)
- Business Cards (Box 2, Folder 13)
- Miscellaneous Career-Related (Box 2, Folder 14)
- Correspondence -- Incoming -- Author Unknown (Box 3, Folder 1)
- Correspondence -- Incoming from Douglas (Box 3, Folder 2)
- Correspondence -- Incoming (Box 3, Folder 3)
- Correspondence -- Outgoing (Box 3, Folder 4)
- Correspondence with Ray Pierre (Box 3, Folder 5)
- Diary, 1946 Jul-Aug (Box 3, Folder 6)
- Correspondence from Europe, 1946 Aug-Sep (Box 3, Folder 7)
- Correspondence from Europe, 1946 Oct-Nov (Box 3, Folder 8)
- Correspondence from Europe, 1946 Dec (Box 3, Folder 9)
- Correspondence from Europe, 1947 Jan-Feb (Box 3, Folder 10)
- Miscellaneous Europe Correspondence and Papers (Box 3, Folder 11)
- Thesis (Box 3, Folder 12)
- Articles by Lomen (Box 3, Folder 13)
- Speeches and Opinions (Box 3, Folder 14)
- Clippings, late 1930s-1945 (Box 3, Folder 15)
- Clippings, 1948-1952 (Box 3, Folder 16)
- Clippings, 1953-1958 (Box 4, Folder 1)
- Clippings, 1960-1991 (Box 4, Folder 2)
- Clippings, 1997-2002 (Box 4, Folder 3)
- Speeches and Scholarly Articles Mentioning Lomen (Box 4, Folder 4)
- Sources Citing "Privileges and Immunities under the Fourteenth Amendment" (Box 4, Folder 5)
- Correspondence about Lomen (Box 4, Folder 6)
- Jennie Berry Correspondence (Box 4, Folder 7)
- Ann Sandstrom-Dean Roland Hjorth Correspondence (Box 4, Folder 8)
- Miscellaneous Documents (Box 4, Folder 9)
- Miscellaneous Library of Congress Photocopies (Box 4, Folder 10)
- William O. Douglas Correspondence (Box 4, Folder 11)
- Miscellaneous Whitman College Material (Box 4, Folder 12)
- Miscellaneous Documents Not Mentioning Lomen (Box 4, Folder 13)